"Anti-Inflammatory Benefits of Berries"
A study following 10,000
Norwegian men for 40 years
found that those
eating berries
more than 14 times a month
were more likely to be alive
at the end of the study.
Higher intake of anthocyanins,
the brightly colored pigments
in berries,
has been associated with
anti-inflammatory effects,
but these are all
just associations.
You can't prove
cause and effect,
until you put it
to the test.
A double-blind, randomized,
placebo-controlled study
found that blueberry smoothies
could turn off
inflammation genes.
This is measuring the expression
of pro-inflammatory genes
in white blood cells
taken from individuals
before and after six weeks
of drinking placebo smoothies
with no blueberries.
They got worse over time.
Six weeks later,
more inflammatory chemicals
pouring out,
whereas the blueberry group
started out about the same
at week zero, but six weeks
of daily blueberries
and the expression
of inflammatory genes
such as IL-6 went down.
Strawberries,
sweet (Bing) cherries,
black raspberries,
extracts of goji berries,
and Indian gooseberries (amla)
have also been shown
to decrease inflammatory markers
in interventional trials.
Have people eat
a largely unhealthy breakfast,
including a bagel
with cream cheese,
margarine, egg,
and a glass of milk,
and the rise
in C-reactive protein and IL-6
over the subsequent six hours
was less when just 10 grams
of strawberry powder,
equivalent to
five large strawberries,
was added to the meal.
A cup of blueberries
was able to significantly blunt
the IL-6 spike
after a ham and cheese sandwich,
and the same with two cups
of raspberries
versus a sausage
and eggs breakfast.
The same amount of banana,
however, was no match,
unable to stop a tripling
of IL-6 levels
within four hours.
Why did the raspberries work,
whereas bananas didn't?
Maybe it's the antioxidants.
Free radicals can disfigure
proteins in our bodies
to the extent
they become unrecognizable
by our immune systems
to the point that our body
attacks them as foreign.
The inflammatory autoimmune
response this triggers
may be prevented, however,
by saturating our bodies
with sufficient antioxidants.
Food selection based on high
total antioxidant capacity
improves endothelial function.
High-antioxidant fruits
and vegetables,
such as berries and greens,
have been found to douse
systemic inflammation
significantly better
than the same number of servings
of more common low-antioxidant
fruits and veggies,
such as bananas and lettuce.
What about apples?
Not only associated
with all sorts of benefits
in observational studies
but proven
to improve risk factors
in randomized
controlled trials,
including inflammation,
but the data is mixed.
Six months of a half cup a day
of dried apple rings
significantly lowers CRP levels,
though the same drop happened
in the control group,
who instead ate about
half a cup of prunes a day.
Freeze-dried apple powder
flopped completely.
Eating three
fresh Gala apples, however,
appears to lower inflammation
both acutely,
within six hours,
and over time.
Six weeks of three Galas a day
lowered fasting levels of IL-6,
though four weeks of twice
as many Shampion variety apples,
a cross between Cox
and Golden Delicious,
didn't seem to have any effect.
What about grapes
for inflammation?
Neither raisins
nor powdered grapes
appeared to help.
What about drinking berries?
Sipping red wine
for 6 to 12 weeks
did not affect
lower inflammation,
compared to gin, water,
or abstention, and acutely,
two to three glasses
of red or white wine
can make things worse,
increasing IL-6 levels
by about 50 percent
within six hours compared
to a nonalcoholic beverage.
However, red or purple
grape juice may help.
Antioxidant supplements
failed miserably.
No anti-inflammatory benefit
was found
for antioxidant vitamins
and minerals
like vitamins C, E,
beta-carotene, or selenium,
which brings us back
to the bright red, blue,
purple anthocyanin
plant pigments.
Dozens of randomized
controlled trials
on anthocyanin-rich supplements,
mostly berry extracts,
have demonstrated
anti-inflammatory effects.
This may be why
red-fleshed plums
beat out
yellow-fleshed apricots
in reducing CRP blood levels.
Or, why even super healthy
fruits like mangoes
may be powerless
against the inflammation
caused by
a Sausage and Egg McMuffin,
whereas a half dozen studies
combined show pomegranates,
a fruit packed with
ruby red anthocyanins,
can bring down inflammation
over time.
The anti-inflammatory effects
of berries are so potent
you can feel it
if you push yourself.
Check out my video Reducing
Muscle Soreness with Berries.
As I note in Watermelon
for Sore Muscle Relief,
eating two cups of watermelon
prior to
intense physical activity
was also found to significantly
reduce muscle soreness.
The researchers concluded
that functional compounds
in fruits and vegetables
can "play a key role
in the design of new natural
and functional products,"
but why design new products
when nature has already designed
everything you need?
Unfortunately, chronic
watermelon consumption,
giving people
a whole watermelon
and a gallon bag
of precut watermelon
every week for 12 weeks,
did not seem to affect
levels of inflammation.
Optimizing recovery
from exercise
is considered the holy grail
of exercise science,
but what about
discernable effects
on inflammatory conditions
such as arthritis?
Tart cherries may be helpful
in treating gout.
Delicious dietary treatments
are much welcomed,
as some gout drugs
can cost $2,000 a dose,
carry no clear-cut distinction
between nontoxic, toxic,
and lethal doses,
or can cause a rare side effect
in which your skin
detaches from your body.
Of course,
the best way to deal with gout
is to try to prevent attacks
in the first place
with a more plant-based diet
and lower alcohol consumption.
Strawberries were pitted against
the most common
inflammatory joint disorder,
osteoarthritis of the knee.
Osteoarthritis patients
randomized to get
about a pint and a half
of strawberries a day
for 12 weeks,
and not only did
inflammatory markers plummet,
they experienced significant
reductions in constant pain,
intermittent pain,
and total pain.
The first clinical study
of the effects of berries
on human arthritis found that
a simple dietary intervention
could have
a significant impact on pain,
inflammation,
and overall quality of life.
Surprisingly, blueberries didn't
seem to have the same effect.
Despite the spin
in the title,
twelve weeks of about four
servings of blueberries a day
had no significant benefit
compared to placebo.
They used conventional
(highbush) blueberries, though,
which tend to have
less antioxidant power
than strawberries
and significantly less
antioxidant
and anti-inflammatory activity
compared to wild,
or lowbush, blueberries.